- Yes, I do.
- (laughs)
My mom doesn't want
to babysit everyday
or any day.
But I need
my mom's help sometimes.
She's just gonna
have to be grandma today.
- You might
have to help me here.
- Oh, see? You gotta
get on your job.
- Am I gonna
be on the payroll?
- What I paid
into this house,
that was salary.
Why should I
have to pay you to watch him?
I thought most grandmas
did it for free.
- This one work
with an app.
I should have
kept this one myself
and gave you the other one.
- Mm-hmm.
He is just too cute.
He looks just like me.
- Everybody keeps saying
he look like Riley.
- Well, Riley look like me.
- I don't know.
Speaking of Riley,
her dad's girlfriend
popped up at the studio
the other day.
- I've been saying to Block,
why won't you
reach out to Riley?
Maybe he knows the vibe
from you to him.
- He made it that way.
I haven't seen her in years.
I haven't talked to him
in like two years,
something like that.
- I would have said,
did you bring the check?
Because you know he owes
pretty close to $50,000.
Now which one
would he rather have,
a lien on his house
or his driver's license
taken?
If I was in Kandi's shoes,
I would have him do an LLC:
lien, license, or cash?
Simple as that.
- But I don't even want to
make this about a money thing.
That part doesn't even
matter to me at this point.
Block is a successful
music industry vet
who has money.
Of course
I could take care of Riley,
but I still think
as her father
he should do his part.
The child support
is what it is.
It would be nice
if he paid it.
It ain't that much,
because he lie about how
much money he had in court,
which, whatever.
But now
he don't even pay that.
It's like come on, dawg.
What is the problem?
- People
take advantage of you
'cause you just
try to be sweet.
- What was I supposed to do,
blast his ass on the radio?
"Cause I've been wanting to
for years now.
Every time
he get on the radio,
telling them,
I'm the million dollar boy.
Old Block love the kids.
I be wanting
to call in on his ass.
Your dead meat ass
does not love kids.
- Now, don't you know what
your mama would have did?
You should have said, hello.
Your ass don't pay
damn child support.
- See, I can't do that.
- Yes, hell, you can do it.
He is gonna pay it.
Or else he just do
like he been doing,
keep his ass away.
- Okay. It's just...
(sighs)
I did tell Riley
that girl showed up,
and I asked Riley
how she felt.
- I feel like
he should be the one,
not his girlfriend.
- I agree.
- You don't wait
till she gets 13 years old
and then now you wanna
step up and be daddy dearest.
- At this point,
Riley's old enough
to say whether or not
she really want to have
a relationship with her dad.
Right now,
she ain't feeling it,
so I'm not going to push
and I'm not going to dis
the relationship.
- You do right
by my daughter.
Ain't nothing good
gonna happen to you.
- Is that what you did?
- I did it.
I did it.
- (laughs)
(Voiceover)
Coming up next...
- Well, you know,
you didn't see a drink
that you didn't want
to throw back.
- Don't tell those lies now.
Wait for the courtroom
for that.
But anyway, so...
- No, she didn't.
- You haven't even
apologized
or owned up to the stuff
that you did before.
How can I trust you?
SFX: Coughing
Argh, my throat!
Ricola Dual Action.
With a soothing syrup center
to relieve  both coughs and
sore throats.
♪ Riiicolaaa! ♪
Right now at Kohl's
it's time to give
the perfect gift
so let him be a kid again
make her sparkle
and help him save the galaxy.
At Kohl's you'll
save a little more
with an extra 15% off
and earn a little
more with Kohl's Cash
so you can give a little
more this holiday.
Kohl's.
From the dairy
farmers of fairlife,
this is our promise.
We bring you richly
indulgent chocolate milk
that's ultra filtered so
fairlife has more protein
and only half the sugar.
And never any artificial
growth hormones.
At fairlife, we
believe in better.
- Hi. Oh, look at you.
You look good.
Nice to see you.
- We look alike.
- Oh, I know.
We do have
similar colors on.
Hell is frosty
because Kenya and I
are actually
in a good place.
- Oh, my gosh,
I have those at home.
- They're beautiful.
- Those are blooming teas.
- I'm taking baby steps.
No need for
a friendship contract just yet.
Well, Phaedra, when you
invite me to your home,
you can serve me that.
- Okay. I
you - I love it. that.
Come on, we're talking
about Phaedra Parks.
All I'm hoping for
is that that voodoo doll
that she keeps of me
in the back
of her drawer,
that she just takes
a few of those pins out.
- Well, I was thinking
about that mystery house.
We really beat you guys.
- Well, I mean, we really were
only playing with two players.
Oh, look in the goggles
in there.
- I think my hair too big.
Porsha,
you got to put them on.
- Let me see, okay.
Girl, my lashes.
- You and Porsha?
- I mean, no, me and Cynthia.
- Don't be shady.
- I'm just saying.
Well, you told me that the whole
point of her inviting us
was to tell us
about her anger management,
and she didn't say
anything about it.
- But no issues
in the room, right?
- No, I mean,
we came there to play nice.
I was, you know,
at least a little
encouraged to be there
knowing that steps
were being taken
for her to control her,
you know, violent tendencies.
- Oh, God.
- And I'm like, okay.
- She is no Rick Flair.
She is not just
whupping up on the people.
- Just some bitches.
She has--Just some what?
- No, I didn't.
(laughs)
- Girl, bye.
I heard you got sassy
with Sheree.
- I got sassy with Sheree?
- That's what I heard.
You called her the B word.
- Oh, no, I didn't.
- You didn't?
- I just said no bitch
is going to tell me
what to do in my house.
That is not me
calling her a bitch.
- So what was it, then?
- It was a generalization.
- Are you going
to apologize?
- What do I need
to apologize for?
She was the one
trashing my house.
- All right.
- Yes, so I mean,
that's what that was about,
so I don't feel
any type of way.
I am still on cloud nine
from Matt's family reunion.
I have my man,
I have my manor,
and Sheree
can take several seats
if she actually had furniture
in her empty house.
- Really what I want
to discuss is my camp.
- Okay.
- In Michigan,
and since
you are Miss Michigan,
I'm sure
you have good ideas.
I began the Phaedra Foundation
a few years ago
when I saw a need in the
community for a mentorship.
This is my son, and he
is who I'm concerned about,
as well as you guys,
and the change begins with us.
I've been very active
in the whole Flint,
Michigan water crisis.
Now I want to do
an overnight camp
specifically for children
affected by the water crisis.
It's going to be a partnership
with the YMCA.
- I learned to swim
at a YMCA.
- Oh, my gosh.
So would you be interested
in helping out
with the camp?
- That'll be cool.
Maybe I could teach the girls
how to dance.
- Oh, yes.
- You know what I always
really wanted to do
is like table manners.
- I love it.
Kenya's crazy as a bed bug,
but at the end of the day,
I can't take away
her accomplishments.
She did earn the title
of Miss Somebody Important.