Must we die?
Are there beings in the cosmos
who live forever...
afloat on an endless journey
down the river of time?
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
Our ancestors
marked the passage of time
by the Moon and stars.
But it was the people
who once lived here,
around 5,000 years ago,
who first starting
chopping up time
into smaller bite-sized portions
of hours and minutes.
They call this place Uruk.
We call it Iraq.
It's a part of Mesopotamia,
the land between the Tigris
and the Euphrates rivers.
The city was invented here.
And one of humanity's
greatest victories was won
in the ceaseless battle
against time.
It was here that we learned
how to write.
Death could
no longer silence us.
And writing gave us the power
to reach across the millennia
and speak inside the heads
of the living.
No one has ever spoken
across a longer stretch
of time's river
than this Akkadian princess,
daughter of the first emperor
in history,
and priestess of the Moon--
Enheduanna.
For not only
did she write poetry,
but Enheduanna did something
no one before her
had ever done--
she signed her name
to her work.
She's the first person
for whom we can say
we know who she was,
and what she dreamed.
She dreamt of stepping
through the Gate of Wonder.
Here's a thought
Enheduanna sent
across more than 4,000 years
to you.
It's from her work entitled
Lady of the Largest Heart.
Innana, the planet Venus,
goddess of love,
will have a great destiny
throughout the entire universe.
...throughout
the entire universe.
And Uruk is also the place
where the epic tale
of "The Hero's Journey"
was first written down.
Before Batman, Luke Skywalker,
Odysseus-- before them all--
there was a man named Gilgamesh
who left home on a quest
to vanquish time.
Gilgamesh was searching
for immortality.
He looked everywhere,
gained complete wisdom,
uncovered what was hidden.
He brought back a tale of times
before the Great Flood.
He built the Wall of Uruk,
which no future king
will ever match.
Read the story
of that man Gilgamesh,
a hero born of Uruk,
who went through all kinds
of sufferings.
Who crossed the ocean,
the broad seas,
as far as the sunrise;
who inspected
the edges of the world,
searching for eternal life.
On his travels,
Gilgamesh encountered
a wise man named Utnapishtim,
who told him the story of a
flood that destroyed the world,
and how one of the gods
instructed Utnapishtim
to build an ark to rescue
his family and the animals.
The earliest surviving account
of the flood legend
was written down in Mesopotamia,
a thousand years
before it was retold
as the story of Noah
in the Old Testament.
So, you could say Gilgamesh
fulfilled his quest
for immortality.
We still read
the Epic of Gilgamesh,
and with every reader,
he lives again.
And all those heroes and
superheroes who have come since
follow in the footsteps
of the first hero's journey--
another kind of immortality;
a story sent from one
civilization to another
across thousands of years.
But life itself sends
its own stories
across billions of years.
It's a message that every
one of us carries inside,
inscribed in all the cells
of our bodies,
in a language that all life
on Earth can read.
The genetic code
is written in an alphabet
consisting of only four letters.
Each letter is
a molecule made of atoms;
each word is three letters long.
Every living thing is
a masterpiece,
written by nature
and edited by evolution;
the instructions
for running and reproducing
the intricate machinery of life.
The essential message of life
has been copied and recopied
for more than 3 billion years.
But where did
that message come from?
Nobody knows.
Perhaps it began in a shallow,
sunlit pool, just like this.
Somehow, carbon-rich molecules
began using energy to make
crude copies of themselves.
Some varieties were
better at making copies,
and left more offspring.
The competing molecules
became more elaborate.
Evolution and life itself
was underway.
Or life could've started
in the searing heat
of a volcanic vent
on the deep sea floor.
Or is it possible
that life came to Earth
as a hitchhiker?
Let me tell you a story
about a traveler
from another world.
The peace of the Egyptian
village of Nakhla,
near Alexandria,
was abruptly shattered
on a June morning in 1911.
Written in this meteorite was
a message from another planet.
But 70 years would pass
before anyone could read it.
In 1976,
NASA landed two Viking
spacecraft on Mars.
Carl Sagan took us there
on our original journey
through the cosmos.
We found that the Martian air
was less than one percent
as dense as ours,
and made mostly
of carbon dioxide.
There were smaller amounts
of nitrogen,
argon, water vapor and oxygen.
A few years later,
when scientists thought
to analyze the gasses
trapped inside
the Nakhla meteorite,
and other members of its class,
they found
a striking similarity--
the vast majority of meteorites
are fragments of asteroids.
But the kind
that hit Nakhla, on Earth,
could only have come
from one place...
Mars.
Welcome to Mars.
Over a billion years ago,
a volcano erupted here
and its lava cooled
into solid rock.
Hundreds of millions
of years later,
this area was flooded
with water.
And long after that flood,
an asteroid the size of
the Rock of Gibraltar
crashed into
the Martian surface,
blasting out a huge crater.
Much of the debris was ejected
back out into space,
where it orbited the Sun
until a gravitational tug
from its home planet, Mars,
diverted one of the boulders
into a collision course
with Earth.
Its arrival shook up
the little village of Nakhla.
Meteorites of the type that
hit Nakhla
are the vehicles of a natural
interplanetary transit system
that sends rocks between
the planets.
Such a meteorite can safely
shelter microscopic cargo--
the seeds of life--
an interplanetary ark.
Most rocks are porous, full of
tiny nooks and crannies,
where life can stow away.
We know
that some microbes can survive
the hostile environment
of space.
Take these guys, for instance.
These microbes spent a year
and a half riding
on the outside of the
International Space Station,
exposed to the extreme
temperatures, vacuum,
and radiation of space.
And some of them
were still alive and kicking
when they were brought back
to Earth.
Even more astonishing
are these creatures,
awakened from a deathlike sleep
of eight million years.
They were frozen
in the Antarctic ice
millions of years before
our species even existed.
And they're still alive.
If life can withstand
the hardships of space
and endure for millennia,
then it could ride the natural
interplanetary transit system
from world to world.
It's a good bet
that our microbial ancestors
spent some time in space.
Why do we think so?
The Earth is four-and-a-half-
billion-years old.
For the first half
of its lifetime,
large asteroids were bombarding
the planet
every few million years.
The most violent impacts
vaporized the oceans
and even melted
the surface rock.
Each such collision would have
completely sterilized
the planet
for thousands of years.
But we know from fossils
in the rocks
that bacteria were evolving
on Earth
during this formative period.
So how could life have survived
such a lethal series of blows?
Whenever one
of those big asteroids
hit the Earth, the explosion
would blast out a crater,
launching millions of boulders
into space.
Many of those rocks carried
living bacteria inside.
Some of the bugs would have
survived in space,
while all those left behind
on Earth would have been fried.
A few thousand years
after each impact,
the Earth would have
cooled down enough
for water to condense
into oceans.
The planet would again be
habitable.
Meanwhile, most of the rocks
launched into space
would have been orbiting
the Sun.
Some of them would encounter
the Earth again,
reenter the atmosphere
as meteorites,
and deliver their precious
cargo of life
to re-seed the planet...
like Noah's ark.
What this means is that life
doesn't have
to start over again from
scratch after each catastrophe.
It can pick up
where it left off.
When the solar system was young,
Venus was probably more
like Earth,
with oceans and maybe even life.
Venus, Earth, and Mars
were all exchanging rocks
with each other,
due to asteroid impacts.
Does life on Earth carry
any traces
of interplanetary voyages
made in the distant past?
Why is it
that some microbes can survive
the intense radiation
and vacuum of space?
These conditions don't naturally
exist on Earth.
Maybe those bugs are telling us
that their ancestors survived
those same conditions in space,
a few billion years ago.
So we know that microbes
can stow away in rocks
and survive the voyage
from planet to planet.
But what about trip
from star to star--
an interstellar odyssey?
The dandelion.
Around 30 million years ago,
it evolved another way to send
its own message of life
through space and time.
Each seedling
is a little paratrooper,
floating on the wind,
risking everything
for a safe place to land.
Updrafts can carry them
higher into the air.
A dandelion can travel dozens,
possibly hundreds
of kilometers,
even crossing over
mountain ranges.
Evolution has shaped it into
an exquisite flying machine.
The seed is another kind or ark,
ensuring the survival
of its species
by riding the currents of the
atmosphere to safe harbors.
Each seed
in its DNA carries a story,
the character and destiny
of the next dandelion--
life propagates
by retelling its story.
Is it possible that life
could survive the journey
from star to star?
The stars are about
a million times farther apart
from each other
than are the planets.
Space is so vast that it would
take billions of years
for a rock ejected
from the Earth
to collide with a planet
circling another star.
Any stowaway microbes
would never survive
the cosmic radiation
for that long.
But there's a plausible scenario
for how life could spread from
one solar system to another.
The stars of the Milky Way
are drawn by gravity
in their own enormous orbits
around its center.
Our Sun, for example,
takes some 225 million years
to complete a single orbit.
During each revolution around
the galaxy,
our solar system will
pass through two or three
gigantic interstellar clouds,
each of them
many light years across.
Galaxies are
world-making machines.
Our Milky Way has more than
100 of these vast clouds,
a place where gas and dust
condense
to form new stars and planets.
In its travels
through the Milky Way,
our Sun is accompanied not only
by its planets,
but also by
a trillion distant comets.
When our solar system passes
through an interstellar cloud,
the gravity of
the massive cloud
stirs up the outermost comets.
Some comets will be hurled out
into the space
between the stars.
Others will plunge inward...
falling towards the Sun.
And some of them may collide
with the planets.
The high-speed impact
of a comet with a rocky planet
will launch boulders
like rockets into space.
If that planet should
happen to be inhabited,
many of those rocks
will carry passengers--
living microbes.
After thousands of years,
fragments of the rocks
ejected from Earth
can fall as meteors into the
atmospheres of newborn planets
in the interstellar cloud.
If the stowaway microbes
should happen to come
in contact with liquid water,
they can revive and reproduce.
This may be
how life comes barreling
into the barren places.
The sun emerges from the cloud,
having scattered
the seeds of life
among the newborn worlds
of other stars.
Those new worlds,
now touched by life,
will then leave
their birth cloud
and go their separate ways.
Eventually, their stars
will carry them
through
other interstellar clouds,
where they may seed
still more new worlds.
Imagine this process
repeated from world to world,
each one bringing life
to others.
Life would then propagate,
like a slow chain reaction,
through the entire galaxy.
This could be
how life came to Earth.
We do not know for sure.
Are there any beings
out there like us?
Do they ask the same questions?
Do they share our fears?
Do they have heroes
and adventures?
If they do exist,
where are they?
How might they make
their presence known?
How did we first announce
our presence to the galaxy?
It was 1946, the year after
the Second World War ended.
The vivid imaginations
of HG Wells and Buck Rogers
never cooked up a more
fantastic experience
than the Army engineers
at their laboratory
in Belmar, New Jersey.
It opens up
unlimited possibilities
for interstellar experiment.
American engineers
bounced a beam
of radio waves off the Moon,
and were able
to detect its echo.
They called this experiment
Project Diana.
It was the first
interstellar message
ever sent by our species...
an eerie, tolling bell.
If one allows
the imagination free reign,
many future
possibilities appear.
Spaceships, carrying passengers
at thousands of miles per hour,
can be controlled
and communication established
with their passengers,
for we now know that
the Earth's atmosphere
can be penetrated.
Traveling at
the speed of light,
it takes just over one second
for a radio wave
to reach the lunar surface.
But the expanding wavefront
is much bigger than the Moon.
Most of the wave
passes right by it,
but the central part
gets bounced back.
After a round-trip travel time
of two and a half seconds,
it hits our planet.
Project Diana transmitted
a series of powerful
radio waves--
one every four seconds--
to "ping" the Moon.
The parts that missed the Moon
are traveling still.
It was just the beginning.
After World War II,
television stations cropped up
all over the United States,
and other parts of the world.
The Project Diana message
and the FM radio, television
and radar signals
of the 20th century
all move outward
at the speed of light.
These transmissions make up
a vast sphere of radio waves,
expanding away from the Earth
in all directions.
You could say that our world
is radiating stories.
Our ancestors etched
the story of Gilgamesh
into clay tablets,
sending that epic tale
into the future.
We've encoded our stories
in radio waves
and beamed them into space.
They cover one light-year
of distance--
that's six trillion miles--
for every year of time
since they were sent.
We've been sending
our stories into space
for over 70 years.
The leading edge
of these signals
has already washed over
thousands of planets
of other stars.
If any of these worlds are home
to a civilization
with radio telescopes,
they could already know
that we're here.
What if other worlds
are sending
their stories into space?
Since 1960,
we've been listening
for extraterrestrial
radio signals
without hearing so much
as a tolling bell.
But our search
has been sporadic
and limited to
certain parts of the sky.
For all we know,
we may have just missed
an alien signal,
looking in the wrong place
at the wrong time.
We've only listened to
a miniscule fraction
of the stars in our galaxy.
And there may be
another problem...
we are, to some extent,
prisoners of our own
moment in time
and the limits
of our technology.
Radio and television
broadcasting
may be only
a brief passing phase
in our technological
development.
When we imagine
alien civilizations
broadcasting signals
with radio telescopes,
are we any different
from earlier generations
who imagined riding
cannon shells to the Moon?
Civilizations even slightly
more advanced than ours
may have already moved on
to some other mode
of communication,
one that we have
yet to discover
or even imagine.
Their messages could be
swirling around us,
at this very moment,
but we lack the means
to perceive them,
just as all of our ancestors,
up to a little more
than a century ago,
would have been oblivious to
the most urgent radio signal
from another world.
But there's another,
more troubling possibility--
civilizations,
like other living things,
may only live so long
before perishing
due to natural causes,
or violence,
or self-inflicted wounds.
Whether or not
we ever make contact
with intelligent alien life
may depend on
a critical question.
What is the life expectancy
of a civilization?
By the time of Enheduanna,
the first person
to ever get a writing credit,
civilization was already
more than 1,000 years old.
But today, her glorious city
is a barren wasteland.
What went wrong?
One problem was
the almost ceaseless warfare
between the cities
of Mesopotamia,
which continually destroyed
their achievements.
They glorified military conquest
and ultimately
became its victims.
Another cause of decline
was that their
technical know-how
overran their
understanding of nature.
The ingenious irrigation system
that was the basis
for the great civilizations
of Mesopotamia
had an unintended consequence--
the water channeled into
their farmlands every year
evaporated and left
its salt behind.
Over generations,
the salt accumulated
and began to kill the crops.
And then, about 2,200 BC,
not long after
the time of Enheduanna,
disaster struck...
a drought of truly
epic proportions,
lasting for many decades.
The rains stopped,
crops withered,
and there was famine
and anarchy.
Barbarians invaded.
The streets of many cities
were littered with dead.
There could be only
one explanation.
Enlil, the supreme god,
was angry because
one of his temples
had been destroyed.
The people of Mesopotamia
could not know
that the same drought
was crushing
the dawning civilizations
of Egypt,
Greece, India,
Pakistan and China.
All the gods of the Earth
must have been really angry
about something.
For all their brilliance,
the people of
those civilizations
had no inkling
they were experiencing
abrupt climate change.
3,000 years later, the climate
would change abruptly for
another glorious civilization,
this one in Central America.
At its peak,
the Mayan civilization
perished,
wiped out by a series
of severe droughts
over the course of a century.
We still carry within us
the echoes of these
extinct civilizations
in our languages and our myths.
Today, we have a single
global civilization.
How long will it live?
There are so many ways
for a civilization to die.
Let's start with the ones
that we probably wouldn't
be able to do much about.
That supernova
is 1,000 light-years away.
If it were much closer, say...
less than 30 light-years
from Earth,
its cosmic radiation
would shred
the atmosphere's
protective ozone layer
and destroy our civilization.
Lucky for us, none of the stars
close enough to harm us
are likely to go supernova
any time in the next
few hundred million years.
Every million years or so,
a supervolcano erupts
somewhere on Earth.
The last time it happened
was 74,000 years ago,
on the island of Sumatra,
in what is now Indonesia.
It spewed
hundreds of times more
rock, ash and toxic gas
than any single volcano
in recorded history.
The molten rock that erupted
from Earth's crust
left this caldera,
100 kilometers long,
now filled with a lake.
The Toba volcano sent
more than 600 cubic miles
of pulverized rock
soaring skyward.
The westward wind carried the
volcanic ash over India,
where it fell out
in a smothering blanket
over the subcontinent.
The eruption loaded
the upper atmosphere
with sulfur gases.
The result was a global haze
that blocked most
of the sunlight
from reaching the surface
for at least five years.
It was like one
five-year-long cloudy day.
This so-called
"volcanic winter"
resembled a "nuclear winter,"
but without the radiation.
Temperatures fell everywhere.
Plants and animals froze
even in the tropics,
dying in enormous numbers.
But life is hardy.
Only a few species
were driven to extinction.
One of our ancestors
in central India
sharpened this stone blade
in the years before
the Toba eruption.
And this blade
was one of dozens
that were found
in the soil layer
above the volcanic fallout.
This tells us that
some toolmakers,
even in the area directly
affected by the volcano,
managed to survive
the cataclysm.
But the global human population
must have plummeted
before rebounding.
If an eruption like this
were to happen tomorrow,
our civilization
would be brought to its knees,
although the human species
would survive.
I can imagine that
our technology
of a few hundred years from now
would allow us to siphon off
the energy of
a threatening supervolcano
before it explodes.
We could then use that energy
for our own purposes.
About once every million years,
a small asteroid
collides with the Earth,
causing a similar amount
of devastation.
With our current science
and technology,
we already know how to prevent
an asteroid impact.
We would see it coming
years in advance
and could send
a spacecraft there
to deflect it into
a harmless orbit.
With the technology
of a thousand years from now,
we might even be able
to mitigate the deadly effects
of a nearby supernova
on Earth's atmosphere.
But what happens
when the danger
to a civilization is invisible?
When no one can see it coming?
Beginning with Columbus,
the European invaders
of the Americas
had a secret weapon that even
they knew nothing about.
They were carrying
bacteria and viruses
for deadly diseases,
such as smallpox,
that the original Americans
had never been exposed to.
The Europeans like to believe
that it was their valor
and superior weapons
and culture
that won them the New World.
The real conquistadors were
the armies of the pathogens
that raced on ahead
to infect and kill nine out
of ten of all the Indians
of North, Central
and South America.
The great civilizations
of the New World
crumbled under the onslaught
of invading microbes.
Without his invisible army,
Cortez and those who followed
might never
have stood a chance.
But what about civilizations
that self-destruct?
Our economic systems were
formed when the planet
and its air, rivers,
oceans, lands,
all seemed infinite.
They evolved long before
we first saw the Earth
as the tiny organism
that it actually is.
They're all alike
in one respect...
they're profit-driven,
and therefore,
focused on short-term gain.
The prevailing
economic systems,
no matter what
their ideologies,
have no built-in mechanisms
for protecting our descendants
of even 100 years from now,
let alone, 100,000.
In one respect, we're ahead
of the people
of Ancient Mesopotamia.
Unlike them, we understand
what's happening to our world.
For example,
we're pumping greenhouse gasses
into our atmosphere
at a rate not seen on Earth
for a million years.
And the scientific consensus
that we're destabilizing
our climate.
Yet our civilization seems
to be in the grip of denial;
a kind of paralysis.
There's a disconnect
between what we know
and what we do.
Being able to adapt
our behavior to challenges
is as good a definition
of intelligence as any I know.
If our greater intelligence
is the hallmark of our species,
then we should use it,
as all other beings use their
distinctive advantages--
to help ensure
that their offspring prosper,
and their heredity
is passed on,
and that the fabric of nature
that sustains us is protected.
Human intelligence
is imperfect, surely,
and newly arisen.
The ease with which it can be
sweet-talked, overwhelmed,
or subverted by other
hard-wired tendencies,
sometimes themselves disguised
as the light of reason,
is worrisome.
But if our intelligence
is the only edge,
we must learn to use it better.
To sharpen it.
To understand its limitations
and deficiencies.
To use it as cats use stealth
before pouncing.
As walking sticks
use camouflage.
To make it the tool
of our survival.
If we do this, we can solve
almost any problem
we are likely to confront
in the next 100,000 years.
And now we've arrived
at the place
where our ancient dreams
of immortality
and modern astrophysics
converge.
Giant elliptical galaxies
are something like... Florida,
where the oldest stars
in the universe may be found.
This is a red dwarf star,
smaller and fainter
than our Sun.
Red dwarfs are by far the most
plentiful stars in the cosmos.
Unlike the Sun, which is
halfway through
its 10-billion-year lifetime,
red dwarfs will continue
to provide light and warmth
to their planets
for trillions of years.
That's hundreds of times longer
than the present age
of the universe.
What would
intelligent beings do
if they had an eternity
to develop their understanding
of the universe?
Perhaps they would learn
how to open shortcuts
in the fabric of spacetime,
to travel between galaxies
faster than the speed of light.
Maybe they would create
whole new universes
as artistic
or scientific experiments.
Of course no one,
or at least nobody on Earth,
knows what
the immortals might do.
If one allows
the imagination free reign.
But what about us?
What is our own future?
What would the Cosmic Calendar
of the next 14 billion years
look like?
If the original Cosmic Calendar
includes all of time
from the birth of the universe
until this very moment...
what would
the Cosmic Calendar look like
for the next 14 billion years?
Just as with
the Cosmic Calendar of the past,
every month the future calendar
equals about a billion years;
every day, some 40 million.
Science makes it possible
for us to foretell
certain astronomical events
in the unimaginably
distant future--
the death of the Sun,
for example.
In some five billion years,
our star will have
exhausted its hydrogen--
the nuclear fuel
that powers it--
becoming a red giant.
I know that sounds depressing,
but if we apply our
intelligence, our descendants
of that distant future
will have long departed
from the lost worlds
of the Sun.
Who knows?
Human events entail
too many variables,
too many uncertainties,
to make scientific statements
about our future.
But we can still dream.
The next golden age
of human achievement
begins here and now--
New Year's Day
of the next cosmic year.
In the first tenth of a second,
we take the vision
of the pale blue dot to heart,
and learn how to share this
tiny world with each other.
The last
internal combustion engine
is placed in a museum,
as the effects of climate change
reverse and diminish.
A fifth of a second
into this future
people will stop dying
from the effects of poverty.
The planet is now
a completely self-sustaining,
intercommunicating organism.
A half-second from now,
the polar ice caps are restored
to the way they were
in the 19th century,
and the forecast
is mild and pleasant
for the next cosmic
minute and a half--
40,000 years.
By the time
we are ready to settle
even the nearest
other planetary systems,
we will have changed.
The simple passage
of so many generations
will have changed us.
Necessity will have changed us.
We are an adaptable species.
It will not be we
who reach Alpha Centauri
and the other
nearby star systems
on our interstellar arks.
It will be a species
very like us,
but with more of our strengths
and fewer of our weaknesses;
more confident, far-seeing,
capable and wise.
For all our failings,
despite our flaws
and limitations,
we humans are capable
of greatness.
What new wonders,
undreamt of in our time,
will we have accomplished
in another generation...
and another?
How far will
our nomadic species
have wandered
by the end of the next century,
and the next millennium?
Our remote descendants,
safely arrayed on many worlds
throughout the solar system
and beyond,
will be unified
by their common heritage,
by their regard
for their home planet,
and by their knowledge that,
whatever other life may be,
the only humans
in all the universe
came from Earth.
They will gaze up
and strain to find
the blue dot in their skies.
They will marvel
at how vulnerable
the repository of all
our potential once was,
how perilous our infancy,
how humble our beginnings,
how many rivers
we had to cross...
before we found our way.
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
www.tvsubtitles.net